你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院的另一个模块
welcome to another module of pwn college
今天我们将讨论内存错误
today we're going to be talking about memory errors
这个视频是对
uh specifically this video is an introduction into uh
这是本课程首次真正开始破坏程序
the 1st time in the course where we'll truly be subverting a program
在过去
in the past
在之前的模块中，我们尝试了逆向软件，试图更好地理解它
on previous modules we've reversed engineered software um to try to understand it better
我们尝试了沙盒逃逸
we've um escaped from jails
我们在使用层面滥用了程序
we've abused programs in terms of their kind of high level design
通过违反程序设计目的的使用方式
by you know using a program there wasn't intended
泄漏文件系统上的敏感数据
to leak out sensitive data on the file system
读取文件系统中的敏感数据
to read out sensitive data on the file system
诸如此类的东西
stuff like this
但在这里，我们真的要黑进软件的核心
but here we're truly going to be messing with the guts of software
让它做一些本不该做的事
to make it do something it wasn't intended to do
我们将讨论内存破坏和其他类型的内存错误
we're gonna cover memory corruption and other types of memory errors
当然，在整个课程中，我们会更深入地研究高级场景
and then of course throughout the course we'll dig deeper into advanced scenarios
我们先后退一步
let's take a step back
看看内存错误的起始
and look at the beginning
当然，这还不是真正的开始
of course this isn't quite the beginning
但也是很久以前了
but sometime a long time ago um
计算机是通过直接输入机器码编写程序的
computers were programmed through the direct input of machine code
不管是直接写在穿孔卡上
whether that was directly on a punch card
通过（根据穿孔卡）在内存中设置位，穿孔卡将被读入内存
by setting bits in memory there the punch card would be read in to memory
还是写汇编代码，就像你在shellcoding时写的那样来
or if it was writing um assembly code like you did in shellcoding to um
让程序完全按照你想的做
make the program do what you um specifically exactly what you wanted to do
当然，这是一个乏味的容易出错的过程
but of course this is a tedious error prone process right
现在大部分软件都不是用汇编编写的
um software is not written in assembly for the most part nowadays
这种不用汇编的趋势始于50年代
um and this uh trend away from assembly started in the 50s um
当时格蕾丝·霍普上将还不是?？
when admiral Grace hopper she wasn't an ？？ back then
提出了第一个编译器
um proposed one of the 1st compilers that
最终变成了COBOL
ended up moving on to become COBOL
在我年轻时非常有名的程序语言
a very famous program language when I was younger
在上世纪末的时候非常重要
was very relevant around the turn of the century uh
因为很多金融软件都是它写的
because a lot of financial software was written by it
所以在2000年前后，它非常重要
and so it was super important around Y2K(year 2000)
它在某些领域很受欢迎
it became popular in certain segments
比如金融部门
such as the financial uh sector
但是它有问题
but it had problems
早期的编译器，它们会生成非常低效的代码
um early compilers they were very um they create a very inefficient code
程序写完，编译的结果跑的不快
you'd write your program and and the output wouldn't run very quickly
另一个问题进一步加剧了这一问题
and this was further compounded by another problem
早期的计算机速度很慢
that early computers were slow
现在这不是问题了
that's not a problem now
所以你会看到很多非常低效的代码
and you see plenty of very inefficient code
例如python解释器
the python interpreter for example is
慢得可怕，但仍然非常受欢迎
horrifically slow but is still extremely popular
但在当时，这是一个严重的问题
but back then this was a serious issue
因为计算机的速度不足以弥补代码的缓慢
because computers were not fast enough to compensate for slow code
20年后
and so 20 years later
Dennis Ritchie也是Unix的联合创始人
Dennis Ritchie also a co founder of Unix
unix算是这门课上你们都在用的Linux的祖先
the kind of um ancestor operating system of Linux which you're all using in this course of course
他为了编写Unix实用程序创造了C语言
uh created C to write utilities for Unix
之后他和同事一起发明了Unix
after that invented Unix with his colleagues
C语言给程序员提供强大的能力
C was specifically designed to provide power  and control to the programmer
同时保持可移植性和
while maintaining portability and
用代码传达复杂的思想和实现复杂算法的能力
ability to convey complex ideas and implement complex algorithms in source code
而且不再需要微调寄存器分配等等
without having to fine tune register allocation and so forth
C语言非常接近于汇编
C maps very closely to assembly
C语言基本上是一种帮你完成函数间寄存器分配等的汇编
C is basically in some sense assembly with the register allocation done for you across functions and so forth
如果你在逆向的时候注意到
and if you notice while you were reverse engineering
如果在逆向工具中单击反编译功能按钮
if you click the decompile function in your decompile button in your reverse engineering tool
或者是用高级的小型表示，基本上就是binary ninja中的反编译
or you went to the high level minivision of representation which is basically the decompilation in binary ninja
你会看到C
you would see C
因为将汇编映射到C语言是最简单的
because it's easiest to map assembly to C
反之亦然
and vice versa
C的诞生是为了创造高效快速的二进制代码
so C was created to enable the creation of efficient fast binary code
同时增加了代码可读性
but still allow people to  interact with something that looks like source code instead of insanity
C在这方面非常强大
C is very powerful in the sense
但是能力越大，责任越大
but with great power of course comes great responsibility
C具有重要的安全隐患
C has significant security implications
c给程序员的能力，能让程序员把系统搞得非常糟糕
the power that gives developers allows developers to mess things up really really badly
问题是大多数开发人员都不是安全专家
and the problem is most developers are not security experts
他们会犯自己都不知道的错误
and they will make mistakes they don't even know about
安全专家当然也会犯错
security experts of course still make mistakes
但他们知道他们的存在
but they even know about them so
写C代码是很危险的，但是有很多C代码
so C code is very dangerous to write but there's a ton of it
70年代，当它被开发出来的时候
and the 70s when it was developed there was the
如果你想写出快速高效的代码，这是最好的工具
really the best tool for the job if you wanted to write fast efficient code
操作系统往往是用C语言编写的
operating systems tend to be written in C
在C语言被开发出来之后，Unix被用C语言重新编写
Unix was rewritten in C after C was developed
Linux是用C语言编写的
Linux was written in C
伯克利系统发行版，催生了其他操作系统
the berkeley system distribution which spawned other operating systems
包括现代的macintosh系列操作系统
including the modern macintosh family of operating systems
是用C写的
was is written in C
所以C突然无处不在
so C kind of suddenly was everywhere
在80年代，人们更关注功能
in the 80s people focus more on features
人们创造了C++语言，基于面向对象概念的c
they created C plus plus the object oriented programming concepts to C
用C + + and
with C plus plus and and
但他们没有解决潜在危险的任何问题
but they didn't fix anything about the underlying danger
在90年代
in the 90s
现代基于VM的语言
the idea of modern  VM based languages
基于Java等语言的虚拟机
virtual machine based languages like java and so forth
出现了，但为时已晚
came about but it was too late
当时主流编译语言占领了所有的领域
um mainstream compile languages were everywhere at that point
Linux诞生了
Linux was born
伯克利系统发行版诞生了
uh the Berkeley system distribution was born
Windows诞生了
windows was born
windows是用C + +
windows is written in uh C plus plus um
所有速度快的编译型内存不安全语言
all fast compiled memory unsafe languages
在2000到2010年，编译型内存不安全语言一直存在
throughout the 2000s compiled memory unsafe language persisted
甚至在整个2010年代
and even throughout the 2010s
人们终于开始思考
people finally started thinking about
好吧，我们如何替换所有的C代码
okay how are we gonna replace all this C code which
用哪种速度快且安全的语言
with something that is still fast um but it's safe
但这只是这项努力的开始
um but it's really just the beginning of of this effort
当然，问题是
um the problem is of course
很多软件都是用C语言编写的
an insane amount of software is written C
C仍然是，取决于你的指标
C is still depending on your metrics
最流行的编程语言
the most popular programming language
如果你去幻灯片上的链接看
if you go to that  index that's linked on the slides
C仍然是第一
C is still number one
在2020年
it's 2020
C语言发明50年之后
50 years almost after the invention of C
它仍然是第一
it is still number one
在从十多年来一直排名第一的java手中夺回了第一
after regaining its spot from java which which was number one for over a decade
C + +是第4
C plus plus is number four
但它是发展最快的语言比python还要快
but it's the fastest growing language out there faster than python
在许多使用场景，它仍然是一种存在内存安全问题的编译语言
and it is still a compiled language with memory safety issues in many use cases
就在2017年，C语言仍然是增长最快的语言
as recent as 2017 C was still the most the fastest growing language
为什么会发生这一切
why is all this happening
这一切的发生是因为
well this is all happening because
抱歉，我愣了一下。这一切都是因为
sorry I blank for a second this is all happening because
随着电脑变得越来越强大
as computers get more powerful
并且似乎能够运行更高级别的语言
and seemingly are able to run higher level languages
你可能会说
right so you might say
为什么我们不能直接用python写操作系统，然后把安全问题搞定呢
why can't we just write our operating systems in python and be done with it
事情并没有那么简单
things aren't quite that simple
有很多嵌入式设备
we have an explosion of embedded devices
你的监控摄像头，门铃，冰箱都是电脑
your security cameras your doorbells your refrigerators are computers
这些计算机很小，速度也不快
and these computers are small and not very fast
他们需要运行得尽可能快的代码
and they need code that runs as fast as possible
所以C语言在所有这些嵌入式设备上大量传播
so there's this huge proliferation of C onto all of these embedded devices
在可预见的未来，它会一直存在
and it's basically fundamentally just here to stay for the foreseeable future
所以我们必须用C语言来处理问题
so we have to deal with problems in C
那么这些问题是什么呢
so what are these problems
这些问题是多重的
these problems are multi fold
但它们基本上源自于C不会束缚你
but they basically stem from the fact that C doesn't hold your hand
C允许你犯错误
and C allows you to make mistakes
我们将在下个视频中深入讨论这些问题
and we'll go into the problems themselves into the at a high level in the next video
但我要指出的是，C语言的问题在很久以前就被大家熟知了
but I'll point out that problems with C have been known a very very long time ago
实际上这些接近底层的计算机语言的问题
actually problems with these sort of low level  computer languages
在60年代末就为人所知
have been known since the late 60s
Robert Graham在一篇论文中介绍了计算中内存保护的基本概念
Robert Graham in a paper about the concept essentially  of memory Protection in computing
在1968年他提出
in 1968 said hey
如果一个程序允许某人重写内存会发生什么
what would happen if a program allows someone to override memory
他们不应该这么做
they're not supposed to do that
这可能导致很糟糕的后果
this might be very bad
而C语言恰恰允许这一点，甚至更多
right and C allows exactly that and more
在下一集视频中，我们将深入探讨C语言允许的操作
in the next video we'll go into at a high level what it is that C allows
不要走开
stay with us